<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>O friends! no friends, to King, Church and state. Or, Thames, Twede and Tyne paraell'd [sic] with Romes Tyber and king-poysoning Po. With positions and practices from Rome and from Rhemes, from Edenburgh and Geneva, poiz'd to some purpose, as the case now stands : and, presented to all impartiall patriots and Presbyterians. / By Veridicus, præterea nihil.</title>
            <author>Veridicus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E432_25</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863161</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863161</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115345</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90114)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115345)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E432[25])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>O friends! no friends, to King, Church and state. Or, Thames, Twede and Tyne paraell'd [sic] with Romes Tyber and king-poysoning Po. With positions and practices from Rome and from Rhemes, from Edenburgh and Geneva, poiz'd to some purpose, as the case now stands : and, presented to all impartiall patriots and Presbyterians. / By Veridicus, præterea nihil.</title>
                  <author>Veridicus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Austin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 20th"; the 8 in imprint date is crossed out and replaced with "7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115345:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115345:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O Friends! No Friends,</hi> TO KING, Church and State.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>Thames, Twede</hi> and <hi>Tyne</hi> paraell'd with <hi>Romes Tyber</hi> and King-poyſoning <hi>Po.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH Poſitions and Practices from Rome and from Rhemes, from Edenburgh and Geneva, poiz'd to ſome purpoſe, as the Caſe now ſtands:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND,</hi> Preſented to all impartiall Patriots and Presbyterians.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Veridicus, praeterea nihil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Auſtin.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115345:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115345:2"/>
            <head>Thames, Tweede, and Tyne paralleld with Romes Tiber, and King-poyſoning Po.</head>
            <p>TO unbowell my acts, yea intentions to the cenſorious and itching times with Athenian eares, deſiring novelties more inſatiably then <hi>Meſſalina</hi> and <hi>Proculus</hi> new luſts, or <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria prima,</hi> the firſt matter, new formes, nothing now venting but newes and toyes, even Bibles themſelves leſſe looked on or after then Bables, Pamphlets, and Ballads, all ſolid books being ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the vulgar as Pearles by Hogs, and Gold by Fools, and turned by miſ-ſpent time into eare-tickling newes, as Religion in our late abuſed peace, in moſt places was turned all into Rites and Ceremonies, as Bottle-Ale into froath, or as they ſay of Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comore trees, their barkes being more then thrir brier: there being lately by a neare friend of mine a Treatiſe pen'd called <hi>Ominous Court Ravens croaking Kings above Lawes,</hi> ſilenced by Lawes ſacred and ſecular, and being as ſoone rejected by as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to ſome Stationers for the preſſe, becauſe it was too ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and judicious for the light headed ſtaggering intoxicated times, fed rather now (like the Goſpells prodigall) with husks, hawes and light Awnes then with ſolid meat, yea with luſted Quailes rather then Manna; I having ſeriouſly peruſed that ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate worke amongſt other diſcuſſions uſefull for the times, (had it ſeene the light) I noted the poiſonous packs and fatall fardells of Popiſh Counſellours, Favorites and Abettors, to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes, fully unripped. Now to ſet footing or to wade after where the unprinted Manuſcript broke the ice, I deſire, as the caſe now ſtands, to anchor all Fluctuations and doubts, that all the blinded eyes in the Kingdome were Swalllow-like, rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with Celedine or Collirium, and that all inſatuated braines were purged with Hellibore, to diſcerne what firme friends Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have been to Proteſtant Princes ever ſince Papiſme, chiefly Jeſuitiſme was hatched (like all other our late renewed Hereſies) from hell it ſelfe: and to look with in partialll eyes into their plots oft effected, if according to their ſanguinnolent poſitions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115345:3"/>commented by their practices in all States, they be not and ever have been as ſure friends to Orthodox Princes, as Hawkes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Doves, Hounds to hunted Hares, Wolves to Lambs, and all kinds of Serpents, from the Baſilisk and great Regulus to the little Dipſas, to all of humane races, yet <hi>hinc noſtri fundi ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitas,</hi> here is our fore-ſeen wrack and woe, that theſe Serpents that we have ſo long fought againſt to cruſh them, as Pigmees againſt Craines, yea as <hi>Meleager</hi> againſt the Calidonian Boare, and the Romane <hi>Regulus</hi> againſt the great Serpent at Bagrada, muſt now by a promiſcuous Toleration of an Hotch-potch and Gallamawfrey of all Sects, if ſome powers as their pates and pens may rule the Roaſt, be warmed againe in the boſome of our Church and State to ſting us to death, whom the ſword of Warre with the effuſion of Hecatombes of blood hath ſo long endeavoured to cruſh and curb like Cockatrices or Crocodiles in their ſhells, or as State-firing, Church-poiſoning Snakes in their heads, which to prevent what afterwards (like Trojans af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-wiſe) we may repent, as well as ruinated Germany, and the Palatinate, by Papall Imperialliſts; let us not be hoodwink'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, nor carried like Hawkes blindfolded on the fiſt, and though Popery now like a little river ſwallowed into a great Sea, ſeem to be drowned in the vaſt gulphs of greater Hereſies, and more horrid blaſphemies then either <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited out in Geneva, or <hi>Simon Magus</hi> in Samaria, or <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> with his <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> or <hi>Arrius,</hi> or <hi>Ebion,</hi> or <hi>Cerinthus</hi> in the Primitive times, or <hi>Munſter,</hi> or <hi>David George,</hi> or <hi>Familist,</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiaſt</hi> in Belgia, or <hi>Ket,</hi> or <hi>Hacket,</hi> or <hi>Ardington,</hi> or <hi>Copping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> here in England, as our zealous Miniſters in London have proteſted againſt them, though now the great Antichriſt, as ſome thinke, now come into the world as the great Dragon hath devoured in a manner Popery the leſſer Antichriſt, as the greater ſound is ſaid to drowne the leſſer, and the greater light to dim the leſſer, yea as Naturians tell us, as a Serpent eats a Serpent before he comes to be a Dragon, yet never the leſſe as a leſſer Bodkin may ſtab a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> every Jeſuitized Papiſt according to their doctrine and practiſes being armed as a <hi>Ravillack,</hi> a <hi>Parry,</hi> a <hi>Lopus,</hi> a <hi>Lupus,</hi> a <hi>Jaques Clement</hi> ſtill, with a Bodkin, a Piſtoll, a poyſon even for a ſuſpected re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Proteſtant. Antagoniſt againſt their Hierarchie, as well as againſt the two French <hi>Henries,</hi> much more a detected Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115345:3"/>to their proceedings, as ſome of the Germane <hi>Fredericks</hi> and <hi>Henries,</hi> and our Engliſh <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. knowing ſtill how to hit the Baſilicall veine, how ever they have lately pretended to be <hi>Caeſars</hi> beſt Catholike Subjects, as good as any man ever hanged upon his hedge, as true friends to him as ever <hi>Iudas</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended himſelfe towards Chriſt, <hi>Ioab</hi> to <hi>Abner,</hi> weeping <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> to <hi>Gedeliah,</hi> Jer. 41.6. yea as the French <hi>Laffin</hi> to the great <hi>Byron,</hi> and our Engliſh <hi>Baniſter</hi> to his Duke, or any other Traytors to Potentates, and States, whom theſe Quoy-ducks have betrayed, as <hi>Sinon</hi> once did Troy, <hi>Zopirus</hi> Babylon, and our Engliſh York Deventree to the Spaniards; yea, however as flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering <hi>Zibaes</hi> they ſtole away the eare and heart of regality for a time ſo farre from true hearted <hi>Mephiboſheths,</hi> 2 Sam. 16.3. as to be thought to ſtand and fight for <hi>Caſar,</hi> and to ſide with him and with his Religion, as the wolves ſhould take part with the Sheepheard againſt the Sheepheards Dogs that keep the Flocks, and that the beſt Centinells over the flocks ſhould be no better then painted Traytors, as though <hi>Cataline</hi> Romes Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand, and his Catilinarians were onely the beſt Bulwarks of and Benefactors unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Senate and the Plebeians, and <hi>Lucius Sicinius,</hi> called the <hi>Achilles</hi> of Rome, and <hi>Marcellus</hi> the Sword of Rome,<note place="margin">De his &amp; Aliis vide Sibel. in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; Valer. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and lingring <hi>Fabius</hi> the <hi>Atlas</hi> of Rome, and <hi>Tully</hi> the Father of his Countrey, and <hi>Codrus</hi> the Father of the Senate, ſhould be counted as <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat,</hi> and <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> were to the Jewes, or every one of them like <hi>Hannibal,</hi> a profeſt enemy and adverſary to the Romans, this were as though <hi>Penelope, Lucrece</hi> and <hi>Suſanna</hi> ſhould be thought as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt as once the Popes <hi>Mazoria,</hi> the Grecian <hi>Hellena,</hi> or any Italian Curtizans and the Corinthian <hi>Lais</hi> and <hi>Thais,</hi> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>Flora,</hi> and our Engliſh Conquerours <hi>Arlet</hi> or Harlot, yea the ſhameleſſe <hi>Paſiphae</hi> were as honeſt as <hi>Abrahams Sarah,</hi> or <hi>Willowbies Aviſa,</hi> ſo incurring by this croſſe-capering, no leſſe then this curſe, of calling evill good, and good evill, light dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and darkneſſe light, Eſa. 5.20. the Crow white and the Swan blacke, a Plebeian a Preacher, a Mechanick a Miniſter, a Dunce a Doctor; a Taylor a Teacher, a Mute a Vowell, a Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man a Divine, and a Divine a Dry vine, a blind Guide a ſeer, a Barne-Babler a brave Benclark, a poore arrogant ignorant a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115345:4"/>Prophet, a cloud a <hi>Juno,</hi> a Figure a Cypher, and a Cypher a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; <hi>Aſinus ad Liram, aſinus ad Tribunal,</hi> an Aſſe a Muſitian, yea an Aſſe a Magiſtrate, and <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe a Miniſter, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Prophets, and <hi>Saul</hi> ſeeking Aſſes a Muſhrump Prophet: in ſuch an Hyſteron Proteron and Phaetonian confuſion, as though this giddy-headed age ſhould turne every thing <hi>topſie turvy, ſuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> de<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> the heavens to ſtand ſtill, as <hi>Celum</hi> once in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mody called <hi>Lingua,</hi> and the dull earth to move, as <hi>Copernicus</hi> once conceited all things running on wheeles, as ſome Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees and Profeſſours rotten at the core, go to heaven the clean contrary way.</p>
            <p>So it is and ſo it hath been for any Jeſuitized Papiſt by his pate, or purſe, or arme, (for all his charmes) to help any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince, to eſtabliſh any Religion, though Epiſcopized, but his owne, as if a Milſtone, or wedges of lead or irons tied a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a ſwiming mans neck ſhould help him to ſwim to the ſhore; or as though a handfull of ſoot, ink, or tar, ſhould better then cleare water, oyle of Lillies, or of Tartar, help a man to waſh his face, and to take out all abſterſive ſpots: I am as ſenſible as the Spider of the leaſt touch of her web, that this preſſed point <hi>in diebus illis</hi> in our ill daies, in <hi>B. Quondams</hi> time had been <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſermo,</hi> a harſh doctrine, it would have incurred either a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencing, chiefly at the Court with, Propheſie not this in Bethell, for it is the Kings Chappell, Amos 7.13. or it might have incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a curriſh cenſure of a ſlit noſe, or a cropped eare in touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Papiſts Favorites to many Prelates, to their little <hi>Laud</hi> be it ſpoken, in many things both politicall and Eccleſiaſticall, as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly ſympathizing as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> Gen. 49.5. or as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> reconciled: amongſt other demonſtrations more then Mathematicall, this is one that for many by-paſt yeares E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy tutoring Regality, that it ſailed betwixt two Rocks, the Scylla of Popery, and the more dangerous <hi>Carybdis</hi> of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritaniſme, as then all true zeal for Reformation was nick-named, of the two evills <hi>minimum eligendum,</hi> the leſſe being to bee choſen, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and two ſucceeding Monarchs after her, were perſwaded that more favour and connivance was to be uſed to the firſt as birds of their owne feather, then to the laſt as more factious, and ſo more perillous to Church and State: And for this purpoſe to make up their mouths, and to ſet a gloſſe and verniſh on their falſe and frivolous ſurmiſes and ſuggeſtions,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115345:4"/>one <hi>Owen</hi> a Papall Proctor, in his Antipareus, and <hi>Omerod</hi> a ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous fellow in his picturé of a Puritan, and the diſguiſed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of <hi>Liſimachus Nicanor,</hi> with many ſuch Panders for the Scarlet Whore, chiefly that great <hi>Dick Eccleſiae Bankcroft</hi> the petty Pope of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in his <hi>Theſes Periculoſa,</hi> out of the writings of ſome Presbyterians, culls out ſome poſitions dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and State-firing, as they are branded, which are wreſted and wrung ſo as a man his noſe till it give blood, and ſo ſet on the Tenterhooks of conſtruction as that Tyrant in Hiſtory racked out every ſhort gueſt to fit a long bed, to the equalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Presbyterians in their poſitions, if not practices, to be as great Antagoniſts to the peace and ſafety of Princes, as the worſt of Papiſts which ever filled the Trojan horſe of any State with the armed Greeks of Traitors: but they may put all in their eyes which they gain by their ſophiſtry and prevarications, making as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> that <hi>Tortus</hi> in his torturing the Greek and Latine Fathers and other Poſtillers, <hi>quid libet ex quolibet,</hi> every thing of any thing: for he that ſeriouſly peruſeth <hi>Vrſinus</hi> his Exercitations,<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Exer. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peter Marter</hi> upon the <hi>Iudges,</hi> chap. 3. <hi>Calvins</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions,<note n="b" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi> Sect. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Daneus</hi> his Politickes,<note n="c" place="margin">lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the Scotch <hi>Buckanan de Iure Regni,</hi> pag. 12.13.58.61. and the zealous <hi>Goodman,</hi> p. 180.184.186. and <hi>Knox</hi> his Hiſtorie of the Church, p. 265. and his Epiſtle to the Engliſh, p. 98. and a book <hi>de Obedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> p. 26.259.139. printed by ſome Exiles in Geneva in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, out of whom pretermitting others, theſe Spiders though from flowers gather poiſon, and he ſhall ſee that the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and reſult of all they write, is onely thus much in effect, that <hi>ſi principes tyrannidem exerceant contra Deum cjuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, eorum ſubditi non tenentur obedire,</hi> if Princes exerciſe tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt God, and his truth and Goſpell, their Subjects are not bound to any active obebience more then the people were obliged by Oath to obey <hi>Saul</hi> in his cruell mandates of maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring the Lords Prieſts, 1 Sam. 22.17. and <hi>Ionathan,</hi> 1 Sam. 14.45. or <hi>Elias</hi> to go to that Idolatrous King who ſent his Captaines of fifties for him, 2 King. 1. or <hi>Eliſha</hi> (after the ſlaviſh ſubjection of the Turkiſh Baſhawes to their <hi>Ottomans</hi>) to yeeld his head to that Tyrant who ſwore to take it of, 2 Kin. 32. or the Jewiſh Captives
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115345:5"/>to worſhip <hi>Nabuchadnezars</hi> Image, Dan. 3.18. or <hi>Irene</hi> to worſhip her Fathers Idolls, which ſhe pulled downe as <hi>Gideon Baals</hi> groves, though with the reluctance of authority, Judg. 6.31. or no more then any were ſubjected to yeeld any obedience to <hi>Maacha</hi> after ſhe was depoſed for her Idolatry, 2 Ch. 15, 16. or to <hi>Athalia,</hi> legally depoſed by <hi>Iehojada</hi> and the Peers of Iſrael for her uſurpations and her cruelties, or to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> after he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded his Regiment for his Leproſies by thoſe Prieſts whoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice he abuſed, all ſubjection being <hi>in ordine quoad Deum,</hi> only in God, for God, and as to God in things legall warranted by God according to the precept and practice of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 5. &amp; Rom. 13.4.</p>
            <p>However for my part, as being <hi>homo eccleſiae,</hi> a man Orthodox and not willing to patronize any errour, if once convicted, if any can prove that ought in theſe recited Authours is errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as he that reads <hi>Scultetus</hi> his <hi>Medulla Patrum, Illiricus</hi> his <hi>Catalogue of the witneſſes of the Truth,</hi> M. <hi>Perkins</hi> his <hi>Apologie,</hi> and the writings of the Fathers, ſhall ſee in <hi>Cyprian, Tertullian, Baſill</hi> and <hi>Augustine</hi> himſelfe, chiefly in <hi>Origen,</hi> groſſe miſts and clouds in theſe and others, counted the lights of the Church, as there is ſome droſſe in every Age in the beſt gold, or if any can prove theſe their opinions to be private Tenets, and not according to the Analogie of faith, nor according to the Nicen and the other three firſt Generall Councells which <hi>Gregory</hi> ſo reſpected, nor according to the 39. Articles agreed upon and received by our Church: then I ſay, I am not bound to plead for them further then the truth is their Proctor, nor tied <hi>jurare in verba magiſtri,</hi> to call them, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> called <hi>Tertullian,</hi> my Maſters, or to reſt on them as the Pithagoreans on their Maſters <hi>ipſe dixit,</hi> as on a Delphick Oracle, ſince <hi>ſequor Cyprianum qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus Cyprianus Scripturam,</hi> I follow <hi>Cyprian</hi> and all other o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo farre as they follow the Scriptures which all muſt ſearch, Ioh. 5. and to whom <hi>ſi runpantur Ilia codri,</hi> if the Devill ſhould ſtorme and all his upſtart Heretikes burſt their guts, we muſt have recourſe, <hi>tanquam ad lidium lapidem,</hi> as to the touch-ſtone of all truths, Acts 11. without which <hi>quid mihi cum centum Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prianis, cum centum Auguſtinis,</hi> what have I to doe with all the Fathers, Councels and Divines ancient and moderne? yet thus much I ſay further for them, though my taske be onely to ſhred them from the poiſonous poſitions of Papiſts, and though my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115345:5"/>reſolutions be not to diſcuſſe nor determine the maine point that exerciſeth the pens, tongues, and pates of all the Politians in the world, howſoever being chiefly ſucceſſive, like the Infantaes of Spaine, the Dolphins of France, and the Princes of Wales, though intrenching upon tyranny, injuſtice, and miſgovernment, may be oppoſed or depoſed, as not willing without a calling, to put my finger in a flame which I cannot quench, ſo I will be ſo farre from a diſtaſted fruit called Medlar, as new perhaps as dangerous to him that meddles with it too much, as once bulls blood to <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> the raw <hi>Polipus</hi> to <hi>Diogenes,</hi> or a <hi>Fico</hi> from a jealous Italian, that I will not ſo much as recite, as I could at large the verdicts of ſome learned moderne Civilians, Divines and Polititians in this ſo much controverted point: but onely like the finger in the Diall, that points at the houre, referre every Sceptick and ſcrupulous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for his ſatisfaction, to <hi>Soto Major de Juſtitia &amp; Iure, queſt.</hi> 4. <hi>art.</hi> 1. to <hi>Vaſquez</hi> in his illuſtrious Controverſies, lib. 1. cap. 26. Num. 22. to <hi>Pizell</hi> in Rub part 1. cap. 2. num. 25. <hi>Gregory Tholoſanus,</hi> that learned Civilian in his 6. Booke of his Common-wealth, cap. 19. as alſo in his 22. Book, c. 7. &amp; 14. and his 23. Book, c. 1. and his 26. Book, c. 4. 7. to <hi>Decianus</hi> his Criminalls, lib. 7. c. 47. to <hi>Covarraus</hi> his various Reſolves, l. 3. c. 6. and to the elaborate <hi>Althuſius</hi> in his Politicalls: But leaſt ſome ſhould object, that theſe produced were Papiſts, profeſt Antagoniſts to Princes unpapized, yet he that is booked, and hath leiſure to read, may ſee their verdicts parallel'd in ſubſtance, by <hi>Gentilis</hi> of the right of Warre, l. 1. c. 23. and by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> though a Pagan, in his Politikes, l. 7. c. 47. chiefly by our moderne learned <hi>Arniſaus</hi> who ſpends many pages in <hi>quarto</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very ſubject of deſcribing, compoſing, reforming, reſiſting, or depoſing a Tyrant: for me to interpoſe my opinion, if not judgement after theſe, were to light a candle to the Sun, though <hi>abſit arrogantia,</hi> I have had a <hi>Caeſars</hi> reſolution of <hi>Iacta eſt alea,</hi> to feare no colours, to beare ſaile in a ſtorme, and have never been wont to be bird-mouthed for a good cauſe, nor to new-trize it with <hi>Metius Suffetius,</hi> to ſleep in a warme skin, nor to be like the Fox and the Mouſe, not to truſt to one ſecuring hole in the ground, or the wall, and though I dare by Gods grace, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as farre as <hi>Luther</hi> once to Wormes, <hi>Jerome</hi> of Prague to Conſtance, or as <hi>Latimer</hi> who was perſwaded his zeale to the truth would coſt him his hearts blood; ſo at this inſtant to ſtand the Church and State in ſtead, however the times ſhould whirle, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115345:6"/>the ſcales be caſt, though I dare do ought legall, though it ſhould be miſconſtrued, <hi>brevibus Gyris &amp; carcere dignum,</hi> worthy of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remies</hi> bonds, or <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſts beheading, yet I ſuſpend my further diſcuſſions, or determinations in this tickle point at this time; yet this maine reaſon obſtructs my pen in this point, theſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigners recited, have given full ſatisfaction in this controverted queſtion, how far the luſts of miſgoverned Kings may be kept within the banks and limits of municipall Lawes; and themſelves, if they be obſtinate in courſes tending to ruination of Church and State, may be moved to better carriage, or removed, as alſo becauſe ſome of theſe alledged chiefly <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſanus</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Lib <hi>24.</hi> Reip. c. <hi>5.</hi> &amp; lib. <hi>20.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Arniſaeus</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">De tyrannide in exercitio.</note>, as alſo <hi>Hottoman</hi> in his ancient Lawes of France, lib. 1. and <hi>Zionetta</hi> in his Tripartite defence<note n="c" place="margin">Part <hi>3.</hi> num. <hi>25.</hi> &amp; <hi>28.</hi> &amp; ſeq.</note>, and <hi>Boſſius</hi> in his book of a Prince<note n="d" place="margin">Num. <hi>55.</hi> &amp; ſeq.</note>, and <hi>Philadelphus</hi> in his ſecond Dialogue of the affaires of France, and <hi>Farinus</hi> in his Criminall Queſtions, with other Humaniſts and Divines, have more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and punctually, proceeded in inſtructing their times what Rights, Priviledges, and Powers the States and Parliamentary Tribunes for a people, have and ever had as true Patriots for their Countries, and State-Phyſitians, to purge out ſuch peccant humours and lop off ſuch unprofitable ſprigs as once <hi>Gave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton</hi> to <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Mortimer</hi> to a French Queene, and ſome ever about <hi>Dioniſius,</hi> and <hi>Allexander,</hi> and <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula,</hi> and <hi>Craeſus</hi> the Lidian, which were the Peſts of Princes, as any may conſult with my Marginalls<note n="e" place="margin">Patritius de Rep. l. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>229.</hi> de Regno, l. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>222.</hi> Antimaehavill, l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>108. 104, 105.</hi> and Tholoſanus de Repub. lib. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>, and made them worſe then they were by nature, but they have alſo aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed power unto them, even to purge the head it ſelfe from the bad fumes of ill counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours diſtempering it; yea to cure even the Kings evill when the diſeaſe grew dangerous ſpreading as a Gangraene, and infectious to all the body politicall and Eccleſraſticall, chiefly when incurable by all admonitory and perſwaſive cordialls, for which cauſe ſuch Parliamentary Peers have ever had, as they ſay, honourable titles of Ephoriſts amongſt the Lacedemonians, of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritians amongſt the Romanes, of Senatours in Venice, of Electors the very pillars, ribs, ſides, and ſtrength of the Empire in Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115345:6"/>many<note n="f" place="margin">Baſes latera co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumna corpus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii, apud Bullam Charoli, <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>3.12, 24.26.</hi>
               </note>, of Rulers, 1 King. 4.1, 2, 3. Elders, Num. 11.16.17. heads of the people, Deut. 33. in Sacred Writ, with other ſuch dignified Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles in Antiquity and Honours, as any may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe more at large in <hi>Cytrem</hi> his Chronicles, in <hi>Zwingers</hi> great Theater, Volumne 8. in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander ab Alexandro,</hi> his Geniall daies, lib. 6. cap. 24. in <hi>Iunior Brutus de Vindice</hi> queſt. 3. and in the 11. diſcuſſion of him that is the Author of the politicall Treaſury, ſuch for authority as the greateſt Princes, even <hi>Darius, Pyrrhus, Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon, Auguſtus, Trajan,</hi> the Romane <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">In Suetonius, Lampridius, Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus his Annalls, l. <hi>1.</hi> and Pliny in his Panegyricks.</note>, the great Perſian <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> Eſther 1.3. the Kings of Iſrael, Jer. 26.10. and the Kings of Nineve, Joh. 3.7. have ever conſulted with uſually with as good ſucceſſe as thoſe that have ſleighted them like <hi>Rehoboans,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred young Phaetons, Green blades, and raſh Rawheads be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, have had ſucceſſe thereafter, 1 King. 12.18.16. yea beſides the powers given them by the body of a people, by theſe recited, he that conſults with <hi>Boterus,</hi> lib. 4. cap. 3. and with <hi>Althuſius</hi> his Politicks, from the 193, 194. pag. to the 223. pag. ſhall ſee theſe Parliamentary powers in a conglobed body of reforming Cenſors and Senators to have been very great in all times, even equallized with theſe <hi>Magna Conſilia,</hi> great Courts in Spaine, and with thoſe great Diets and Aſſemblies in Germany, and the great Court in Paris, and that <hi>Rota Romana</hi> and other places of Judicature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Venetians, Polanders, Rhaguſians, and other parts, ſo extolled by that great Beuclark <hi>Budaus</hi> in his laſt book of his Senate, and by <hi>Hottoman</hi> in his Hiſtory of France, cap. 10, 11. and by <hi>Borrheus</hi> of the Authority of the great Counſell, num. 170. yea not to be like <hi>Plutarks Lamia,</hi> quick-ſighted abroad, and to ſhut up our eyes at home, he that conſults with our Oxfords caſe in his Politicks, lib. 3. cap. 5. and with Sir <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> in his Engliſh Government, lib. 2. cap. 2. ſhall receive much ſatisfaction, unleſſe he be hoodwinkt, how farre a legall Parliament may curb, direct, or correct what is meerely regall in a Perſian humour or Tumour of <hi>quod libet licet,</hi> of every luſt for law, which is illegall, eſpecially by peruſing the elaborate paines of our Teologicall Lawyers, M. <hi>Pryn</hi> in the Parliamentary paſſages in Hungary, France, Suevia, Spaine, Italy. Bohemia, Denmarke, Scotland, and how farre they have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115345:7"/>been improved againſt ſuch Princes as have ſplit the ſhip of State by miſgovernment, or dilacerated their people by tyranny, or ſpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them by injuſtice, ſuch men-Monſters for Monarchs as were once <hi>Ecclinus</hi> in <hi>Sabellicus</hi> his Chronicles, lib. 8. cap. 3. and <hi>Phereus</hi> in <hi>Tullies</hi> Offices, lib. 2. and <hi>Melancthons</hi> Chronologies, lib. 2. and <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> in <hi>Joſephus</hi> his Antiquities, lib. 13. cap. 18. as alſo <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crinus, Nero, Phraates, Vedius Pollio,</hi> and many more, whoſe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies as incurable as cruell, are fully related by <hi>Tholoſanus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and the French <hi>Bodin</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>, in their Common-wealths, by <hi>Lipſius</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, and <hi>Danaeus</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>, in their Politicks, by <hi>Valerius</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Lib. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>, and <hi>Aelianus</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Lib. <hi>13.</hi> &amp; <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>, in their Hiſtories, <hi>Melancthon</hi> in his Chronicles, lib. 4. and <hi>Gorlicius</hi> in his Politicall Axioms, Axiom. 16. theſe with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more<note n="o" place="margin">The three Herods Maximium, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus, Adonize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck, Scylla, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius.</note>, how farre they have been croſſed, limited, bridled, cenſured in the ſevereſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, all may better drink at the fountaines heads and be ſatisfied in their ſcruples, by conſulting the large Tracts of the Authors quoted, then by my poor pitchers, if I ſhould draw ought or lap ought from them, as Poets in another ſtreame out of <hi>Homers</hi> baſon.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being thus premiſed, it being <hi>extra alam,</hi> without both the ſphaere of my purpoſe, and not correſpondent to the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this Tractate, to diſcuſſe this maine controverted point, how farre Regality turned to Tyranny may be oppoſed or depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, about which moſt Civilians, yea Divines alſo, are as much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, <hi>pro &amp; contra,</hi> as the Poetized Deitles in <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Virgil,</hi> about the Grecians and the Trojans, ſome ſiding with the one, ſome with the other, <hi>Mulciber in Trojam, pro Troja ſtabat Apollo,</hi> ſo that I may <hi>hoc agere,</hi> keep me only to my propoſed and intended point, to cleare our Engliſh Thames and Scotch Twede from running in ſuch ſanguinolent ſtreames of regall and legall blood eſtuſed, both by guns and gownes in war and peace, as ſome lay to their charge in ſuch Torrents and Heeatombes as have run daily from Po and Tiber, to the turning all States where Jeſuits have acted, into red ſeas of blood, and waſhed Proteſtant Princes out of their Thrones: for which cauſe to open the eyes of the blinded Baalites, and to ſtop the mouths and blunt the horned pens of ſuch blatrant beaſts as <hi>Jurwicius</hi> in his booke of the Profeſſors of the fift Goſpell, of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115345:7"/>
               <hi>Poſſevine,</hi> in his booke of the Atheiſme of Proteſtants, of <hi>Rainolds</hi> in his <hi>Calvins</hi> Turciſme, of <hi>Gifford</hi> in his Preface before that book, of <hi>Feverdentius</hi> upon <hi>Jude,</hi> of <hi>Turner</hi> in one of his Orations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of <hi>Cocleus, Bolſecus, Eudaemon, Scurrilous Kelliſon</hi> in his Survey, and other Romiſh <hi>Rabſhekahs</hi> who divulge all puritanicall Proteſtants no better then Atheiſts, worſe then Turks, Jewes, worſt of Heretikes in the Church, worſt of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Catilnarians in all States, <hi>Liſymachus Nicanor</hi> ſtretching much to parallel them in the laſt with the worſt of <hi>Pontificians</hi> in his Invectives either for a larger Rotchet, like <hi>Parſons</hi> once, and <hi>Eccius,</hi> or for a <hi>Cardinalls</hi> Hat, or for a Miter with <hi>Wolſey:</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the former imputations be abundantly cleered, and retorted upon themſelves by Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> in his Tetraſtilon, by <hi>Gabriel Powell</hi> and Doctor <hi>Beard,</hi> in their learned bookes of Antichriſt, by Mr. <hi>Squire</hi> upon the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> Doctor <hi>Sutcliffe</hi> in his Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Papiſme, Doctor <hi>Feild</hi> in his fift book of the Church, and many more, yet to quench this laſt brand, caſt upon both our Patriots and Presbyterians of being as ſmall friends, nay as inteſtine foes to all <hi>Caeſars</hi> and their ſafeties, as the moſt malignant Maſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, peſtilent Prieſts, and Jebuſiticall Jeſuites, as fire may come forth from the repercuſſions of ſlint and ſteele; I deſire to light a candle of truth to all ſorts from our Dan to Berſheba; yea to this preſent and to future ages throughout Europe, to ſee the evident difference as much betwixt them, as betwixt Wolves and Lions, Doves and Serpents, in theſe ſubſequent poſitions, practiſes, poſtures, and paſſages propounded in theſe Queres.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what Belgick Scotch or Engliſh Puritan (no not <hi>Browne, Penry,</hi> nor <hi>Martin Mar Prelate</hi>) ever preached or printed, that Princes, if they be Heretikes and Tyrants, of Papiſts new minting and moulding, that is contradictory in judgement and practice to every novell Opinion, Idolatry, Superſtition and Hereſie in their Hierarchy, not downe right for the Antichriſtian Papacie, but chiefly if ſo oppoſite to them and their Dotages in Doctrine and Diſcipline, that they ſeeke to reſiſt cruſh or curb their blaſphemies by Statute, Lawes, Edicts, Mulcts, Decrees, Exiles, Impriſonments, as Chriſtian Emperours have done, (what ever Anabaptiſts and Libertines blatter to the contrary) as appeares by <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his life of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> lib. 3. cap. 62.63. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Explication upon <hi>Luke</hi> cap. 15. as alſo by <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> in his 48. Epiſt. and ſome Conſtitutions of the two <hi>Theodoſians</hi> and others in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115345:8"/>Law<note n="c" place="margin">Vide Theodoſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> cod. de Trinitate &amp; Cunctis cap. de Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note>, that then as abſolute Tyrants, they may <hi>eo nomine,</hi> be depoſed, being firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, as were the <hi>Othoes, Henries</hi> and <hi>Fredericks</hi> in Germany, <hi>Childerick</hi> in France, and our Engliſh <hi>Deborah</hi> here in England, by five Popes, their great Monarch of the Church (as they call him) ſupreme under Chriſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving power <hi>in ordine ad Deum,</hi> in his relation to Chriſt, to depoſe ſuch Kings and diſpoſe their Kingdomes, as once from an <hi>Henry</hi> to a <hi>Rodulph</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Petradedit, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro petra, Diadema Rodulpho.</note>: did ever <hi>Calvin, Danaeus, Knox, Buchanan, Goodman,</hi> broach any ſuch Doctrine as this which is writ in the blood of Kings by <hi>Creſwell,</hi> in his Philopater, pag. 194. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> in his unjuſt Tractate of Juſtice, Tract. 2. Diſp. 39. p. 149. <hi>Saunders</hi> in his viſible Monarchy, lib. 2. cap. 4. pag. 70. <hi>Coſter</hi> in his Enchiridion, part 1. pag. 64. and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> their great <hi>Goliah,</hi> in his fift booke of his Pope, cap. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, what Puritan called Cathariſt, and Novatian in S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, and now Presbyterian or Parliamentary, yea where did any Synod of the whole Presbytery, or Senate of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Patritians, ever abſolve all Subjects from all ſubjection and ſubordination, from all obedience ſworne by ſolemne Oaths, from ſuch Princes as the pillars, Catterpillars and Proctors for Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in their ſenſleſſe ſenſes, in their Mints and Forges make He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticall or Tyrannicall (that is to ſay juſt and zealous Proteſtants) Oathes, being the onely ties and Obligements which Princes have to ſecure their Crownes and lives; when did ever any Puritan, (unleſſe they will make ſuch impure ones as Munſter and Familiſts in Belgia, and <hi>Straw, Cade, Tiler,</hi> and other Rebells in England, the ſcum and froath of men, Puritans) when I ſay, did they ever unty this Gordian knot, as both by their tongues and pens, (laviſh, looſe and poiſonous) many of them, and not of the meaneſt fools, have attempted, as amongſt the reſt <hi>Azorius</hi> in his Inſtitutions, cap. 15. ſexto, and <hi>Maſſonius</hi> the Lawyer in his Majeſty of the Militant Church, part 2. lib. 4. pag. 676. <hi>Simancha</hi> a Biſhop in his Inſtitutions, Tit 23. Sect. 11. <hi>Cardinall Tolet</hi> in his Inſtructions (or Deſtructions) for his Prieſts, lib. 1. cap. 13. <hi>Creſwell</hi> in his Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater pag. 194. with <hi>Gregory de Valentia,</hi> upon <hi>Aquinas</hi> his Sums, Diſp. 1. q. 2. punct. 2. p. 463. and <hi>Bannes</hi> the Schoole-man on this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Doctor, 2. 2. q. 12. Art. 2. Conc. 2. the Decretalls of their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115345:8"/>Popes, eſpecially ſtriking with the great Hammer, to the mauling of Monarchs, as of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh in Gratian, Cauſa. 15.9.6. and of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth, lib. 5. tit. 7. cap. 5. <hi>Gloſſa</hi> with all the bleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Calves of Babell, ſuch as <hi>Allen, Parſons, Saunders,</hi> after the roaring bulls of <hi>Pius</hi> (or <hi>Impius</hi>) the fift, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as they have been well baited by many a valorous Papiſtomaſtix, chiefly by <hi>Michael Rhemigerus,</hi> Anno Dom. 1582. as alſo by him that hath writ the booke called <hi>Brutum Fulmen,</hi> ſcoffing the Papall paper ſquibs and <hi>Balaams</hi> curſes in their Excommunications of the French Kings.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, howſoever Puritans falſly nick-named, that is zealous and Oxthodox Proteſtants may teach, that Princes whether ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive or ſucceſſive, ſubordinated to Lawes divine and humane, may be bridled by State <hi>Ephoriſts</hi> in their unlimited humours and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and kept in as the Hollanders the feared inundations of the Sea within banks, chiefly when their ſurging waves are ſwell'd by the winds of ill Counſellours; and withall as wife men uſe Law and Phyſick, <hi>tanquam ultimum refugium,</hi> as their laſt refuge, that Subjects <hi>ſe defendendo,</hi> by that Law which nature dictates ſelfe-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to man, birds and beaſts, may take up defenſive rather then offenſive armes, as endangered <hi>David</hi> did when he was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a Partridge over the Mountaines by ſanguinolent <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. 22.2. and as <hi>Mardocheus</hi> and the Jewes ſtood upon their Guards, when their lives were ſought and plotted by <hi>Haman,</hi> Eſther 9.16. as alſo in defence of the Municipall Lawes of a Kingdome, or for the prevention of the ruination of a Kingdome, by the confederacy of home-bred viperous Tyrants and Forraigne inteſtine enemies; yet nevertheleſſe. when did any Presbyter or Patriot excite Subjects, as our Jeſuiticall Firebrands do, to take up armes againſt a Proteſtant King, and to kill him who ever can, by ſword, piſtoll or poiſon, no more ſparing him then a Beare or a Wolfe in ſuch caſes of Treaſon, in ſuch caſes of Injuſtice, Hereſie, and Tyranny, as Satan hatcheth and coddles in their Serpentine heads, that is, being not wholly leavened with their Romiſh Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, worſe then that of the Scribes and Phariſees, when did ever Edenborough or Geneva ſend forth ſuch a Trojan horſe filled with the armed Greekes of treaſonable poſitions, ſuch as are vented or vomited in this kind, extant <hi>Cum Privilegio,</hi> by <hi>Gregory de Valentia,</hi> Tom. 3. Diſp. 2. punct. 2. by <hi>Simancha,</hi> in his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, tit. 23. ſect. 12.13. by their <hi>Rainaldus</hi> in his Roſaeus, pag. 157.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115345:9"/>by <hi>Bannes</hi> on <hi>Aquinas,</hi> 2.2.9.12. art. 2. which King-killing and State-firing Tenets of theirs as they took effect in the Rebellions of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. in Germany, perſecuting <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour with fire and ſword, as we may ſee at large in the Chronicles of <hi>Cranzius</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſpergenſis,</hi> and in <hi>Oneale</hi> the Iriſh Rebell againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſo alſo in the French, bearing Armes againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the third, deprived of his Crowne by Papall Inſtigation, as we may ſee in the book Extant of his juſt abdication, pag. 262. with ſuch like bloody Pageants, as <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Saul</hi> the third plaid againſt our <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and ſix Popes, namely <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. <hi>Verban</hi> the 7. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 14. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 9. and <hi>Clemens</hi> the 9. againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. of France ere they butchered him, and nine Popes even <hi>Paul</hi> the 4. <hi>Pius</hi> the 4. <hi>Pius</hi> the 5. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. <hi>Verban</hi> the 7. and the 9. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclement Clemens,</hi> and the 9. <hi>Nocent, Innocent,</hi> againſt our <hi>Albions Eliza,</hi> all whoſe ſpleens ſhe out-lived.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, what Scotch or Genevean Presbyter, ever approved or applauded the baſe and bloody acts of any Traytor againſt his legall King, as Pope <hi>Xiſtus</hi> the fift in a ſolemne Oration amongſt his Cardinalls, Anno 1589. hiperbolically extolled <hi>Jaques Clement</hi> aſſaſſinating the French <hi>Henry,</hi> as may be ſeen in the printed pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, pag. 3. 5. 8. 9. 10. equalizing his fact with the acts of <hi>Ehud, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith, Harmolaus, Timoleon, Brutus,</hi> and other Patriots, who rid their Countries of Tyrants, as King <hi>Edgar</hi> rid England of Wolves.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, when did the whole Sanedrim of Proteſtant Patriots in any Country, or all the united Claſſes of Presbyterians ever aſſume unto themſelves theſe more then humane Titles and prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives, which are given to the Pope and his Hierarchy by <hi>Bertach</hi> in his Repertory, part 4. in dict. Papa, by <hi>Bozius</hi> in the nature and rights of the Church, lib. 5. cap. 10. pag. 476. by <hi>Muſcovius</hi> in his Majeſty of the Militant Church, lib. 1. cap. 1. pag. 26. and by the extant Ceremonies of the Church, lib. 1. ſect. 5. pag. 4. fol. 61. chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when did they ever aſſume to themſelves that power which the Canoniſts and Clawbacks give even in temporalls, beſides ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, unto their Antichriſtian Popes, as to be the heads over all the Kings of England, France, Ireland, Spaine, Denmark, Portugall, Scicily, Suevia, Arragon, Naples, Hungary, Ruſſia, Croatia, Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, yea over all Nations and Potentates, depoſing whom and when they pleaſe, and diſpoſing their Crownes and Diadems
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115345:9"/>ſpurning them off as with their feet, as they dealt with <hi>Leo</hi> the third, <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt, <hi>Frederick</hi> the firſt, <hi>Childerick</hi> of France and others.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, when was ever any ſuch Luciferian Doctrine broached that any Patriot or a whole Senate of them, and a Colledge of Presbyters in tranſlating Empires, as <hi>Zachary</hi> did the Empire of Greece to the Tutonicks, as though their Hierarchy being but the firſt begotten of the Devill, as <hi>Polycarpus</hi> called <hi>Marcion,</hi> ſhould out-vie the brag of their father in diſpoſing the Kingdomes of the earth, Mat. 4.9. to thoſe that would worſhip the beaſt in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Papall pride, then ever was read of in <hi>Alexander, Clitus, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian, Coſroes, Herod, Sapho, Hanno,</hi> and others affecting Deities.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, what pen from Patriot or Presbyter ever juſtified the bold and bloody intrenchments and uſurpations of any ſpirituall perſon above ſecular powers, about which <hi>Parſons</hi> hath drawne his ſteeled and rapier-like pricking pen in his Dolman, part 2. pag. 62. <hi>Bellarmine de Pontifice</hi> l. 5. c. 6. &amp; 7. and <hi>Allen</hi> in his extant Letter to Sir <hi>William Stanley,</hi> with the reſt of their Proctors and Factors.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, though the Patriots and Presbyters attribute very much to thoſe whom the people, as in a conglobed body, chooſe to be their Tribunes for them in Parliaments, as I have noted from Civillians, as namely, to ſtand for their Freedomes and legall Priviledges; 2. For their Proprieties, not to be ſpunged nor ſqueezed, nor ought reav'd from them, as once <hi>Elies</hi> ſonnes by fleſh-hookes, 1 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. as alſo againſt Caterpillars, and Monopolizing Officers, and all that ſhould invade their civill Right, or exhauſt ought from them, more then ſhould be given according to the Cuſtome in Spaine, in a Parliamentary way, as Auxiliaries to their Cuſtomes and Crown-Revenues, as alſo to ſee that State-vipers be not hugged in the boſomes of Kings, chiefly ſuch as ſhould ſo farre poiſon regall ears that Law-makers may be ſo farre Law-breakers to doe what they liſt, when and with whom they liſt, yet they teach not with <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> in his Romane Pompifex, lib. 2. cap. 7. <hi>&amp; de Clericis,</hi> cap. 2. that Kings have no authority from God, and from his Law, but from the Law of nature, and that their power is ſo immediately in and from the multitude as in the proper Subject, that the people may make a King, which otherwaies ſhould be no King, but as a private man, as he depreſſeth Regality under this maine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny headed beaſt, in his bookes of Laicks, lib. 4 cap. 6. and of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115345:10"/>lib. 2. cap. 19. yea ſo farre doth vaſſalize them under a Plebeian yoke, that if ſuch a King degenerate to be a Tyrant, that is, in his ſenſe a Proteſtant, <hi>à populo poſſe deponi &amp; eligi alium,</hi> the people may depoſe him and chooſe another, as though all the Hive ſhould riſe againſt the Maſter Bee, and throw him out of <hi>Platoes</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, yea ſaith <hi>Gregory de Valentia,</hi> tom. 3. diſp. 2.9.12. punct. 2. <hi>Si crimen Hereſis ita ſit notoria,</hi> if his Hereſie (that is ſtill the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Orthodox truth) be ſo palpable that it cannot be concealed, that is to reject a Maſſe as a Maſſe of corruption, which was the Hereſie of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> and hold the Papall Hierarchy is (it's by ſo many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned pens) to be Antichriſt, then <hi>ante Judicis ſententiam,</hi> before any publike Judicature, <hi>ſubditi licitè poſſunt negare obſequium,</hi> his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may lawfully deny their obedience, yea as proceeding <hi>à malo ad pejus,</hi> from evill to worſe, from Potentialls to Injunctions, <hi>omne operam dare debent ſubditi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saunders</hi> in his viſible Monarchy, lib. 2. cap. 4. his Subjects muſt beſtirre themſelves like Bees to peerk another preſently into his place. Indeed <hi>Mariana de Rege,</hi> c. 6. p. 59. &amp; 60. though his booke was burnt in Paris for his good Divinity, with more cauſe then <hi>Pareus,</hi> pauſing as it were, a little leiſurely; he would have this Hereticall Prince firſt to be warned, <hi>à Comitiis Regni,</hi> of the Patriots of a Kingdome, but if he be as <hi>Origen</hi> was once called <hi>Adamantinus,</hi> and as <hi>Luther</hi> of a reſolute and ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantine ſpirit, that he is grounded in his opinion, then <hi>in ejus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam licet quicquam attentare,</hi> like a hunted Wolfe or wild Boare, any may knock him in the head, any ſturdy Rogue like the Italian <hi>Bandetti,</hi> may be his aſſaſſinate, yea and be renowned for the act as a ſecond <hi>Codrus</hi> or <hi>Junior Brutus,</hi> and be regiſtred in red Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as a Saint in the Romane Rubrick, with S. <hi>Faux,</hi> S. <hi>Ravillack,</hi> S. <hi>Garnet,</hi> as if S. <hi>Cain,</hi> S. <hi>Judas,</hi> S. <hi>Job,</hi> as many ſpurs and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are put to the ſpeed of the zealous Amorettoes of the Scarlet Whore to vindicate her in this kind, as many may ponder them with amazement from the porcupined pens of <hi>Squarez</hi> in his Defence of the Faith, l. 6. c. 4. ſect. 14. of <hi>Santarellus</hi> in his Tractate of Schiſme, of <hi>Mariana</hi> in his book <hi>de Rege,</hi> l. 1. &amp; 6. of <hi>Eudemon,</hi> or <hi>Cacodemon, ali-as Andra</hi> in his Apologie for <hi>Garnet,</hi> of <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in his Pedagogue of weapons, of <hi>Martin Becan</hi> in his Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall Sins, and of <hi>Arturus</hi> in his Books of the Church, it being a Scythian cruelty thinks the roaking Raven <hi>Mariana</hi> in his booke alledged, l. 1. c. 6. p. 58. for a private man not to right his Father
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115345:10"/>and Mother groſſely wronged, much more to neglect his Conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and his common Mother the Common-wealth in ſuch a caſe as this, though <hi>non vox hominem ſonat O Demon certè,</hi> not the voice of a man, but of a Devill is roaring in his pen terribly as in a Pump, in ſuch noiſes as were never heard in the Colledges at Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, Glaſcow, and Aberden, nor in the Churches of Geneva, nor in that Synod in Weſtminſter, much leſſe in the Senate, Thames and Twede were never ſo poiſoned and polluted with black inke, like the black ſcum which the fiſh Scylapendra caſts from her to trouble the waters, much leſſe ſtained with red inke from the Baſilicall veines of Kings, who ſtood for the Arke of Religion, or to throw downe the Dagon of Idolatry, or Superſtition; in ſuch poſtures as every regalized <hi>Gideon,</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Joſias,</hi> and zealous <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> ought to be, that aimes at the glory of Chriſt Crowne, and the ſplendor and ſafety of his own Crown.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, as reflexing a little further on what I have touched, when did ever any Proteſtant, Patritian, or Presbyter, ſpurre up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Traytors to ride from Tiber to Tiburne by their encomiums and commendations, extolling old and new Patricides as much as <hi>Cardan</hi> did his <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Catiline</hi> or <hi>Carolus Scribanius</hi> in his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitheater of Honours, <hi>John Guiner</hi> the French Traytor, cap. 12. expoſtulating with his Popes why they will ſend forth no more ſuch <hi>Timoleons, Dions,</hi> and <hi>Philopoemens</hi> as he was to rid France of her <hi>Tarquins, Dioniſians, Machamdams, Ariſtotemiſts,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>ſeculorum portentia,</hi> men Monſters, as his Pope Rhetorick ſtiles them: <hi>Campian</hi> alſo the Popes Champion, <hi>Braſtow, Saunders,</hi> and others as much extolling <hi>Penniman,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Holtthrop,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch Catilnarians as ever <hi>Hercules</hi> was for quelling <hi>Cacus, Cerberus, Hidra, Meleager</hi> for killing the Calidonian Boare, our S. <hi>George</hi> in Helyn, Warwicks <hi>Guy,</hi> or <hi>Bevis</hi> of Hampton, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dning Dragons, Lions, Gyants, and Monſters.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, when and where did any of our Senators and Synods diſgorge ſuch King-quelling and Church and State-firing Poſitions rightly poized and parallell'd as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his fift booke of his Pope, and his third book againſt <hi>Barklay,</hi> and in his Tractate of the office of a Prince, and <hi>Turrian</hi> in his firſt book, and third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Church, and <hi>Becan</hi> in his Theologie, part 2. cap. 3. tract. 1. chiefly <hi>Swarez</hi> moſt of Square in the Defence (or rather Offence) of the Faith, lib. 3. cap. 17. ſect. 18. cap. 23. ſect. 18.20. lib. 45. cap. 16. ſect. 1. l. 16. c. 16. ſect. 16. to whoſe peruſalls I refer my Intelligent Reader.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115345:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115345:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115345:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115345:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115345:13"/>
            <p>Eleventhly, to come from Lightning and Thunder to Bolts, from their Poſitions bad and bloody enough to their worſe practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as they ſay of Cockatrices, Foxes, Wolves, and all kind of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, as of ſome Zelanders, that <hi>creſcunt nequitia ſimul acereſcente ſenecta,</hi> that they grow <hi>à malo ad pejus,</hi> ever worſe and worſe, <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jores aves aetas tulit,</hi> they being now birds of a more bloody fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their predeceſſors, as we feele bleeding experiments by their combuſtions in England and Ireland, being all of them now borne as it were, with teeth, as was ſaid of <hi>Cham</hi> or <hi>Zoroaſtes:</hi> And a little to grapple with them as claſped ſhips, and ſpur with theſe ſpurred Cocks, when did ever any ancient or moderne Presbyters called Puritans, by their tongues, pates, pens, agitations factious fractions, raiſe ſuch warres amongſt and againſt Princes, kindle ſuch jarres in Cities, States, Kingdomes and Countreyes, as Tibers Jeſuites have done in France, Italy, Germany of late, and the Palatinate, as alſo Moravia, Bohemia, Lions, Paris, Merindoll, Calabria, in the times of <hi>Iohn de Roma</hi> and <hi>Minerius,</hi> as alſo in Poland, Anno, 1591. in Belgia, Anno, 2584. 1594. 1598. in Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covy, Tranſilvania, the Dutcheſſe of Auſtria, the Marquiſate of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia, Anno, 1608. 1009. as appeares by the Chronicles of theſe States, as alſo of the Belgicks, tom. 1. 519. as alſo in Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, Anno Dom. 1627. 1628. and of their like bloody and boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Pageants, let the judicious ſee them Anatomized fully by <hi>Pelargus</hi> in his Preface to his Jeſuitiſme, by our <hi>Omerod</hi> in his picture of a Papiſt, by <hi>Gregory. Hieromonachus de Fraude Ieſuitaram,</hi> of the frauds of the Jeſuites by a booke extant, <hi>de turbis Ieſuitarum in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riente,</hi> of the troubles of the Jeſuites in the Eaſt, by Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 8. eſpecially in his Bull printed againſt them, and by the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites Catechiſme, compoſed by their Prieſts, who beſt ſtudied them, pag. 430. <hi>ad</hi> pag. 528. by <hi>Watſon</hi> alſo in his Quodlibets, and divers others ſo unripping their Fardells, that all that will open their hood-winkt eyes may ſee, that <hi>non cum Ieſu itis, itis ſi cum Ieſuitis,</hi> in faith, in fact, who with a Jeſuite doe run, they croſſe way run from Jeſus quite, anſwering their names no more then bloody <hi>Antiochus</hi> called <hi>Epiphanes,</hi> or then <hi>Zacheus</hi> before his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, or <hi>Judas</hi> to be the praiſe of God, or that <hi>Theophilus</hi> who was <hi>Origens</hi> great enemy, or that <hi>Bencocas</hi> in the daies of <hi>Adrian</hi> a great Impoſtor like them, deſcribed by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> Hiſt. l. 2. c. 28. &amp; l. 4. c. 7. proved <hi>Bencoſba</hi> the ſon of lying, yea no more anſwering their names, then that <hi>Pſeudo-Maſtapha</hi> in <hi>Lanclavins</hi> his Annalls
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115345:13"/>pag. 34. and that <hi>Pſeudo-Alexander</hi> in <hi>Joſephus</hi> his Warres, l. 2. c. 5. and that counterfeit <hi>Nero</hi> in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> Hiſt. l. 18. p. 58. and that counterfeit <hi>Wooldemar</hi> in <hi>Marchia,</hi> in <hi>Peucers</hi> Chronicles lib. 5. pag. 60. or that counterfeit <hi>Agrippa</hi> in <hi>Cuſpiman,</hi> in <hi>Tiberio,</hi> p. 13. or that artifizing <hi>Smerdis</hi> in Perſia in <hi>Justin,</hi> pag. 26. or that ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Parkins</hi> and <hi>Lambert</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. time, in our owne Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, and in <hi>Cambdens</hi> Remaines, pag. 241. were reall Kings, whoſe parts they Hiſtrionically acted on bloody Stages, like our Jeſuites, though they were but baſe Peaſants, as farre from Princes as our pride-puft Plebeians from gifted and called Preachers; theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed (and not our Presbyterian Puritans, or Patriots) as all juſt pens have branded them, <hi>Cathedrae Peſtilentiae,</hi> the Chaires of Peſtilence, the Turrets of Hereſies, the Pandoraes Box of Church-diſeaſes, the fatall Palladiun filled full of Treaſons, the chiefe Panders and Bawdes of the Scarlet Whore, the <hi>Academies</hi> of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, the Aſſaſſinates of Kings, poiſoners of Kingdomes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwers of Cities, Incendiaries of States, Legates for Satan, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents for Hell, Oppoſites to Heaven, and the very Phaetons of the world; which to demonſtrate more then Mathematically, as we have traced the caſe with them abroad, ſo we might joyne iſſues with them at home in nearer diſcuſſions, and ſo it will appeare <hi>luce clarius</hi> as evident as the light, that the firebrands of ſedition, and the greateſt Antagoniſts to the ſafeties of our Engliſh <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars,</hi> have been ever Jeſuitized Romaniſts hugged in the breſts of ſome States, as vipers in their boſomes, and growing up by them as Elder Trees in walls to their ſubverſion, and bringing downe even by ſuch a blind and bloody zeale, as by a Hotch-potch Toleration, and by a Liberty, ſuch Libertines as the late deſtructive Belgick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts would againe plant amongſt us, as legally as the Jewes with their <hi>Thalmud,</hi> and Turkes with their <hi>Alcoran;</hi> ſuch as theſe will appeare to be thoſe that have been, are, and will be not onely the diſturbers, but deſtroyers of our Iſrael, and not thoſe that are as unjuſtly taxed and traduced for ſuch factious and ſeditious Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries, as once <hi>Elias</hi> was branded by <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 King. 18.17. and <hi>Paul</hi> by <hi>Tertullus</hi> to be a peſtilent fellow, a mover and Ringleader of ſedition, Acts 24.5: I know well, that all theſe ſanguinolent commotions writ with bloody inke by <hi>Sleidan</hi> in his Hiſtorie, lib. 22, &amp; 28. by <hi>Oſtander</hi> in his Epitomized Centuries, Cent. 16. p. 626. <hi>Cuſpinian</hi> in his Gallican Church, p. 625. <hi>Ferres</hi> in his Hiſtorie, p. 588. and by <hi>Chitraeus</hi> in his Chronicles, p. 71. are laid upon Calviniſts,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115345:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115345:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115345:15"/>on new Reſormers, and new Reformation, even as Satans Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece the Powder plot, had it taken effect, had been malignantly fathered upon the Puritans, I know alſo that ſanguinolent ruſtick warre in Germany for the time and manner exceeding in cruelty, and deſtruction, any faction that I have read either in France, Anno, 1335. or Venice, 1310. or in Auſtria, 1456. or in Vienna by the Plebeians againſt the Senate, Anno, 1462. or in Padua, Florence, Millaine, Parma, Genoa, or elſewhere, as it's tragically penned by <hi>Munſter</hi> in his Coſmography, <hi>Sleidan la Gaſt,</hi> and <hi>Hondorſſius</hi> in his Theater, fol. 358. as it was more tragically acted by <hi>John a Leiden,</hi> and his Familiſts: I ſay I know this is laid upon the ridged Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, as the fomenters of it, and Ring-leaders in it, but they may as well tax them, for all theſe commotions made by the Begards and Beguines in Germany in <hi>Charles</hi> the 5. time, or by the naked Adamites in Bohemia, or by the Fratricells in <hi>Bergomas</hi> his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle, lib. 19. or by <hi>Dulcinus</hi> and <hi>Margeret,</hi> Anno, 1308. and their Anabaptiſts in <hi>Platina,</hi> and in the Sums of Counſells, or by the Crucigerians, with the Banner of their bloodie Croſſe, ſo patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally bleeding yet, in <hi>Tholoſanus</hi> his Common-wealth, l. 13. c. 8. from pag. 912. to 920. as alſo cap. 13. pag. 440. &amp; cap. 19. pag. 974. yea as juſtly may all theſe troubles and ſhakings of our Church and State now, by our new Seekers for the man in the Moon, and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, be taken from the right Davuſſes, and heriticall blaſphemous white Devills turned Angells, and be laid on our Orthodox Divines which caſt on the waters of the Sanctuaries on their wildfires, from <hi>Styx</hi> and <hi>Avernus</hi> as to tax Proteſtants with the Belgick blood ſhed by Anabaptiſts, againſt whom we know how ſolidly and vehemently <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Bullinger</hi> hath writ, as alſo how <hi>Luther</hi> hath zealouſly declaimed, hath Munſter the Pſeudo-Prophet of theſe ſanguinolent Anabaptiſts, and declared himſelfe againſt theſe Enthuſiaſts, as freely as ever <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt the Donatiſts, <hi>Cyprian</hi> againſt the Novatians, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> againſt our inſpired Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and our London Miniſters, yea M. <hi>Edwards</hi> himſelfe in his Gangraena and Anti-Toleration, againſt our Muſhrump Preachers, and in moſt points blaſphemous Hereſiarkes, withall it's well knowne, that not onely D. <hi>Baeſon</hi> in his learned Tract <hi>de Obedientia,</hi> of Obedience, and D. <hi>Hackwell</hi> in his <hi>Scutum Regale,</hi> his Buckler for Kings, and D. <hi>Morton</hi> mauling <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Prince, Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly if not Machavilianly drawne, but many more both ſound heads and honeſt hearts have preſcribed all legall obedience unto
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115345:15"/>Kings, <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad Aras,</hi> ſo farre as <hi>Caſar</hi> doth not intrench upon Gods part and prerogative, nor on the publike good of his people, for whom he is placed a Sheepheard to protect them and feed them, not a Wolfe in ſheeps cloathing to pluck them nor feed on them; it's my hope and deſire that all may be ſatfsfied with theſe Parallels betwixt Twede and Tyber, which our owne experiments tell us ſpawned ſo many Traytors even in Queen <hi>Elezabeths</hi> time, as <hi>Yorke, Squire, Babington, Tichburn, Parry, Lopus</hi> that <hi>Lupus,</hi> and more then a good many others, for Tiburne, as their marchings thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the rode and broad way of Treaſon were directed and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by Cardinall <hi>Allen,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Como, Parkins, Creſwell,</hi> and other Incendiaries, Factors for Hell, and actors for the Papall Hierarchy, compounded of lying equivocation, forgery, humane policy, Machavilian plots, hell-hatched ſtratagems, and all the powers of darkneſſe to exalt it ſelfe above Chriſt his Kingdome, his Ordinances, his Word, his Will, his Worſhip, and whoever is called a Terreſtriall God, in trampling upon all Scepters terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to exalt one Miter with a triple Crowne, ſpirituall, temporall, and infernall; from all which exorbitances how farre all true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants differ, (once nick-named Puritans, as Chriſt was called a Galilaean, and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> once <hi>Sathanaſius</hi>) let any judge, that are not drunk with Romiſh dregs, French philters, or halfe poiſoned with Iatalian Ficoes, and he ſhall with an unpartiall eye ſee as much diſcrepance betwixt Proteſtants, Patriots, and Patricidians, as <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boleth</hi> and <hi>Shiboleth</hi> made betwixt Ephraimites and Giliadites, and as Civilians make betwixt errours in Regality, and terrors in Tyranny.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
